I'll be going through the initial camera calibration steps
最初のカメラキャリブレーションのステップを
in this Jupyter notebook.
このJupyterノートブックで行います
The first step will be to read in calibration images of a chessboard.
最初のステップではチェス盤のキャリブレーション画像を読み込みます
it's recommended to use at least 20 images to get a reliable calibration.
信頼性の高いキャリブレーションにするには少なくとも20枚の画像を使ってください
And for this example,
この例では
we have a lot of images in this calibration images folder.
このキャリブレーション画像フォルダー内に多数の画像があります
They are all images of a chessboard, taken at different angles and distances.
すべて 異なる角度と距離から撮影したチェス盤の画像です
And there's also a test image. I'll eventually want to test my
テスト画像もあります  最終的には
camera calibration and undistortion on.
カメラキャリブレーションをテストして歪みを補正します
Each chessboard here has eight by six corners to detect.
各チェス盤には8かける6の検出すべきコーナーがあります
I'll go through the calibration steps for
最初のキャリブレーション画像の
the first calibration image in detail.
キャリブレーションステップを詳しく見ていきます
First, you can see that I've already done my Numpy OpenCV and
まず すでにNumpy OpenCVを実行し
plotting imports.
インポートをプロットしてあります
Then I'll read in the first image calibration1.jpg, and I'll display it.
次に最初の画像 "calibration1.jpg" を読み込んで表示してみます。
So here's our calibration image.
これがそのキャリブレーション画像です
I'll map the coordinates of the corners in this 2D image,
この2D画像のコーナーの座標
which I'll call it's image points, to the 3D coordinates of the real,
これをイメージポイントと呼びますが  これを現実の 歪みを補正した
undistorted chessboard corners, which I'll call object points.
チェス盤のコーナーの3D座標 これをオブジェクトポイントと呼びますが これにマッピングします
So, I'll set up two empty arrays to hold these points, object points and
これらのオブジェクトポイントとイメージポイントを保持する2つの空の配列を
image points.
セットアップします
The object points will all be the same.
オブジェクトポイントはすべて同じです
Just the known object coordinates of the chessboard corners for
8かける6の盤のチェス盤のコーナーの既知の座標
an eight by six board.
にすぎません
These points will be 3D coordinates, x, y and z from the top left corner,
これらのポイントは3D座標x y Zであり左上のコーナー
0, 0, 0, to the bottom right, 7, 5, 0.
0 0 0 から右下の7 5 0までです
The z coordinate will be zero for
z座標はどのポイントもゼロです
every point, since the board is on a flat image plane.
盤はフラットな画像平面上にあるからです
And x and y will be all the coordinates of the corners.
またxとyはすべてコーナーの座標です
So I'll prepare these object points,
これらのオブジェクトポイントの
first by creating six by eight points in an array.
準備として まず 配列に6かける8のポイントを作成します
Each with three columns for the x, y, and z coordinates of each corner.
それぞれ各コーナーのx y z座標のための3カラムがあります
I'll initialize these all as zeros using Numpy's zero function.
Numpyのゼロ関数を使用して すべてゼロに初期化します
The z coordinate will stay zero so I'll leave that as it is but for
z座標はゼロのままなので そのままにしておきますが
our first two columns, x and y
最初の2つのカラムxとyについては
I'll use Numpy's mgrid function to generate the coordinates that I want.
Numpyのmgrid関数を使用して必要な座標を生成します
mgrid returns the coordinate values for a given grid size and
mgridは与えられたグリッドサイズの座標値を返し
I'll shape those coordinates back into two columns, one for x and one for y.
これらの座標を2つのカラムに戻します  1つはx 1つはyです
Next, to create the image points, I want to look
次にイメージポイントを作成するために
at the distorted calibration image and detect the corners of the board.
歪んだキャリブレーション画像を見て 盤のコーナーを検出します
OpenCV gives us an easy way to detect chessboard corners with a function
OpenCVにはfindChessboardCornersという名前の関数があり
called findChessboardCorners that returns the corners
見つかったコーナーをグレースケール画像で返すので
found in a grayscale image.
チェス盤のコーナーを簡単に検出できます
So I'll convert this image to greyscale and
この画像をグレースケールに変換して
then I'll pass that into the findChessboardCorners function.
findChessboardCorners関数に渡します
This takes in our greyscale image along with the dimensions of the chessboard
これはグレースケール画像とチェス盤のコーナーの寸法を
corners.
取ります
In this case, eight by six, and the last parameter is for any flags.
この例では 8かける6であり 最後のパラメーターはフラグです
And there are none in this example.
この例では ありません
If this function detects corners,
この関数がコーナーを検出したら
I'll append those points to the image points array.
それらのポイントをイメージポイント配列に付加します
I'll also add our prepared object points,
準備したオブジェクトポイント
objp, to the object points array.
objpもオブジェクトポイント配列に付加します
And these object points will be the same for
これらのオブジェクトポイントはすべての
all of the calibration images, since they represent a real chessboard.
キャリブレーション画像で同じです  現実のチェス盤を表すからです
Next, I'll also draw the detected corners,
次に 検出されたコーナーを描画するために
with a call to drawChessboardCorners,
drawChessboardCornersを呼び出します
that takes in our image, corner dimensions and corner points.
これは画像 コーナー寸法 およびコーナーポイントを取ります
And I'll display these corners so
これらのコーナーを表示すると
that we can see what was detected in an interactive window.
検出されたものをインタラクティブウィンドウで確認できます
So let's run this code.
では このコードを実行しましょう
Here's what our detected corners look like.
検出されたコーナーはこのようになります
And if I zoom in, it looks like the corners were detected pretty accurately.
拡大すると コーナーはほぼ正確に検出されているように見えます
The next step will be to do this for all the calibration images.
次のステップでは これをすべてのキャリブレーション画像に対して行います
I can read in all the calibration images by importing the glob API,
すべてのキャリブレーション画像を読み込むにはglob APIをインポートします
which helps read in images with a consistent file name,
これは一貫したファイル名で画像を読み込むのに役立ちます
like calibration one, two, three, and so on.
キャリブレーション1 2 3などです
Then, I'll iterate through each image file, detecting corners and
次に各画像ファイルについてコーナーの検出と
appending points to the object and image points arrays.
オブジェクトポイントおよびイメージポイント配列へのポイントの付加を繰り返します
Then later, we'll be able to use the object points and
その後 オブジェクトポイントとイメージ ポイントを使用して
image points to calibrate this camera.
このカメラをキャリブレートできます
I'll show you the OpenCV functions you'll need to calibrate the camera and
カメラのキャリブレートと画像の歪み補正に必要なOpenCV関数について
finally, undistort images.
説明します
To calibrate a camera, OpenCV gives us the calibrateCamera function.
カメラをキャリブレートするために OpenCVにはcalibrateCamera関数が用意されています
This takes in our object points, our image points, and
これはオブジェクトポイント イメージ ポイント および
the shape of the image.
画像の形状を取ります
And using these inputs, it calculates and
これらの入力を使用してひずみ係数を計算し
returns the distortion coefficients and the camera matrix that we need
3Dオブジェクトポイントを2Dイメージポイントに変換するために必要な
to transform 3D object points to 2D image points.
カメラ行列とともに返します
It also returns the position of the camera in the world, with values for
また ワールド内のカメラの位置を
rotation and translation vectors.
回転および変換ベクターの値として返します
The next function you'll need is undistort.
次に必要な関数は undistortです
This takes in a distorted image, our camera matrix, and
これは歪んだ画像 カメラ行列 および
distortion coefficients.
ひずみ係数を取ります
And it returns an undistorted, often called destination image.
そして歪みのない、デスティネーション画像と呼ばれるものを返します
In the next quiz, you'll need to apply what you've learned to calibrate
次のクイズでは 学習したものを応用してカメラをキャリブレートし
the camera and correct for image distortion.
画像の歪みを修正する必要があります
Good luck.
頑張ってください